Finding Aid for Michigan Photographers Society photographs
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Photographers Society photographs circa 1880-1925
Michigan Photographers Society.
92531 UBP.3 2; UBP.3m
Organization of Michigan photographers; collected copyprints of historical images.
0.3 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The photographs were donated by the Society (donor no. 5833 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
The Michigan Photographers Society is an organization of Michigan photographers established to collect and preserve the photographic history of Michigan.
The collection consists of copyprints (with some negatives) of historical images collected by members of the Michigan Photographers Society. The photographs are arranged alphabetically by name of city where the collector lived. This is followed by descriptions of the images. The strength of the collection is for its visual documentation of various Michigan cities, including street scenes, businesses, private residences, views of ships, railroads, lumbering activities, and local customs.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Agricultural machinery.; Automobiles.; Blacksmithing.; Boat and ship industry.; Business enterprises.; Carriage and coaches.; Carts and wagons.; Charlevoix (Mich.); Charlotte (Mich.); Construction industry.; Detroit (Mich.); Dwellings.; Ferris, Woodbridge N., 1853-1928.; Football.; Flint (Mich.); Grand Haven (Mich.); Grand Haven (Mich.)--Lifesaving stations.; Greenville (Mich.); Harbor Springs (Mich.); Health resorts.; Howell (Mich.); Industrial buildings.; Interiors.; Laborers.; Lansing (Mich.); Lifesaving stations--Michigan--Grand Haven.; Lumber industry.; Mancelona (Mich.); Mills.; Mount Clemens (Mich.); Muskegon (Mich.); North Branch (Mich.); Parades and processions.; Pontiac (Mich.); Port Huron (Mich.); Political parades and rallies.; Railroad accidents.; Railroad stations.; Railroads--Michigan.; Rural schools.; Saginaw (Mich.); Sebewaing (Mich.); Ships--Great Lakes.; Street-railroads--Michigan.; Tornadoes.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Collected copyprints of member photographers
  (no negatives unless otherwise indicated)
  - Charlevoix, Mich.; Mancelona, Mich. Area (Box 1, Folder 1)
    (from Robert C. Miles, Charlevoix; copyprints made by A. E. Arnold, Royal Oak)
    - Gov. J.W. Begole visits Charlevoix 1884
    - Mancelona area lumbering
    - Mancelona farmer's house)
    - Lumbermen, unidentified location, 2 items
  - Flint, Michigan (Box 1, Folder 2)
    (from Baldwin-Chase Photographers, Flint)
    - Palace Vaudeville Theatre 1920s
    - 1st annual reunion of old employees of Durant-Dort Carriage Co. circa August 1925
    - Western Union messenger boys outside office, Flint 1920s
  - Grand Haven, Mich. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    (negatives; from Murray R. White, Grand Haven)
    - Wholesale Grocery Supply circa 1890
    - Store circa 1890
    - Mechanics Ship Yard, on the Grand River circa 1875
    - Cutler House, mineral baths, opened 1872
  - Greenville, Mich. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    (folder no. 4; from Abe Helmut, Greenville)
    - Unlabelled two storefronts, presumably Greenville, probably 19th century
    - Terpsichorean Club dance, Phelps Opera House circa 1908
    - Electric lights on the main street 1909
    - Greenville Fire Dept. 1912
    - "pulling stumps at Edmore, Mich.", 5 items
  - Harbor Springs, Mich. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    (from Virgil D. Haynes, Harbor Springs)
    - Ice tramway at the Knickerbocker Ice Co. 1899
    - Resorters boating at Harbor Point on Little Traverse Bay circa 1910
    - Young Ottawa Indian inducted into the tribe before Chief Pipi-qua (Fred Ettawageshik) 1946
    - Ottawas cutting wood for the "Fathers" of Holy Childhood Church and School 1900
    - Ray Freeland with his homemade ice sled, 5 items
  - Howell, Michigan (Box 1, Folder 6)
    (from Duane Zemper, Howell)
    - Old thrashing outfit traveling through Oak Grove, north of town
    - Townspeople dressed as Indians in parade, riding in old car
    - Oldest picture available of a uniformed team in Howell, the Oceola Giants
    - Early football action shot, the Howell High School team circa 1912
    - Old steam-powered sawmill 1890s
    - Theodor W. Shindorf, blacksmith, and his assistants outside his shop
    - Unusual shot of the interior of an old blacksmith shop
    - A. E. Parker outside his garage and small machine shop, c-1915
  - Howell, Michigan (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - The inside of an early machine shop
    - The outside of the old implement shop
    - Early picture of the north end of Howell Lake
    - The old grist mill, at this time, after 1900 owned by A. O. Hoyland
    - Ex-Governor Woodbridge N. Ferris speaks at a large rally
    - Old county schoolhouse with students and teacher outside
    - Autos from Lansing and points between parked on Howell's main street as part of the celebration as the Wolverine Paved Way-a brick road from Detroit to Lansing--neared completion 1915
  - Miscellaneous towns (Box 1, Folder 8)
    (from Edward F. Hicks, Lansing)
    - Main Street, Charlotte, Mich.
    - Belle Isle
    - Ferry, Detroit circa 1912
    - Saginaw St., Flint, Mich. circa 1890
    - Pere Marquette depot and train, Howell, Mich. circa 1915
    - Lansing street scene with Capitol in distance circa 1880
  - Miscellaneous lumbering photos, unidentified localities (Box 1, Folder 9)
    (from Del Conkright, Mt. Pleasant)
    - Loading at the spur; Michigan,1800s
    - The Big Wheels with loads 1800s
    - Saw mill at rail head 1800s
    - Floating restaurant for loggers 1800s
    - Big Wheels with horses and oxen 1800s
    - River dogs 1800s
    - Log bridge and crew 1800s
    - The "Big Wheels" 1800s
    - Railhead spur; 1800s
  - Mount Clemens, Mich. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    (from Fred Henk, Mount Clemens)
    - Map of Mount Clemens 1875
    - Drawing of Macomb County Court House, Mount Clemens 1840-1880
    - The passenger boat Mineral City [sailing on the Clinton River?]
    - Clinton River transportation-sailing and steam boats that brought freight from other nearby ports. 1870-1920
    - Steamer Lily-coal boat
    - Passenger steamer Uarda, Mount Clemens, on her way to Walpole Island Indian Reservation, Canada
    - Sailing ship Bertie at Mount Clemens dock
    - City of Mount Clemens, coal-lumber boat
    - S.S. Roberta of Mount Clemens-excursions to Walpole and Harsen's Islands, and fishing trips in Lake St. Clair
    - Grand Trunk R.R. station where Thomas Edison learned telegraphy
  - Mount Clemens, Mich. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Macomb County Court House (1880-1929), early 1900s
    - Downtown Mount Clemens 1890
    - Home of Christian Clemens, founder of Mount Clemens
    - 1897-funeral car plunges into Clinton River at Mount Clemens
    - Mount Clemens Hunting and Fishing Club, located on Lake St. Clair off the mouth of the Clinton River, before 1900
    - Blacksmith and carriage shop
    - Cyclone hits Mount Clemens May 25, 1896
    - Mount Clemens first mineral bath house circa 1890
    - St. Joseph Sanitarium under construction 1899 mineral bath house
    - Amusement park 1905
  - Muskegon, Michigan (Box 1, Folder 12)
    (from Leonard Kooiman, Muskegon)
    - Brinman Lumber Mill 1889
    - Log rolling on Muskegon Lake circa 1887
    - Lumber men's homes 1889
    - Street car riot ? 1918
    - Jefferson St.
    - Western Avenue 1889
    - Western Avenue
    - Original Coast Guard Station at Muskegon
    - Lake Harbor Channel, Muskegon
    - Docks-lumber mill on Muskegon Lake
  - North Branch, Mich. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    (from Bob Peet, North Branch)
    - Miscellaneous street scenes and lumber mill, 5 items
  - Pontiac, Mich. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    (from R. H. Frye, Pontiac)
    - S. Saginaw St., Pontiac
    - Corner E. Lawrence and Perry
    - Unlabelled store front scene
  - Port Huron, Mich. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    (from Israel Photography, Port Huron)
    - Huron Ave. looking north
    - Huron Ave. looking South
    - Lumber industry
    - Home of Sam Edison (father of Thomas Edison)
    - Water Street looking west (from military)
  - Saginaw, Michigan (Box 1, Folder 16)
    (from Don Pahl, Saginaw)
    - Miscellaneous street scenes, including Genesee Ave. and corner Washington Ave. and Genesee St.; miscellaneous lumbering scenes, including birdseye view of W. D. Young & Company buildings, Bay City, 8 items
  - Sebewaing, Mich. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    (folder no. 17; from Hurdlebrink Studio, Sebewaing)
    - Downtown Sebewaing, early 1900s
    - Logging near Sebewaing, early 1900s
    - Sugar beets on way to Michigan Sugar Co.
    - Sebewaing, early 1900s farming
    - Sebewaing area, early 1900s
    - Bach cider and wine press mill 1914
  - Freeport, Mich.
    (from Edward Hicks, Lansing)
    - Addison Herrington Family, about 1902 (Folder 1)
  - Muskegon, Mich.
    - Boy sitting on bank of Muskegon River circa 1900 (Folder 1)